Costco's Big Secret: It Doesn't Play by the Rules
To say that Costco has a legion of fans is no exaggeration.
More than 51 million people ponied up more than $3 billion in membership fees in 2023 to get access to Costco and its mega-discounts.
Zachary Crockett, a reporter at the daily business newsletter, looked closely at what's driving the cultish devotion towards the global chain,
and why the retailer is doing so well even as consumers do more and more of their shopping online.
What is Crockett's take?
Costco has succeeded by flipping conventional business wisdom on its head by putting its customers' interests ahead of its shareholders'.
That's evident in its profit margin. By Crockett's calculations, the average markup at Costco is 11% compared to the 25% to 50% average markup in the retail industry.
And the price being marked up is often lower than what consumers will find elsewhere.
This is thanks to Costco's purchasing power.
Take, for example, a pound of wagyu beef.
That pound of beef, which costs Costco $100, would theoretically cost a Costco shopper $111.
However, that same pound at a regular grocery store would cost the consumer $140, due to a higher markup and a higher purchase price for the grocer.
As an example of just how little Costco tries to squeeze its customers, consider this anecdote.
At a time when Calvin Klein jeans typically cost around $50, Costco sold them for $29.
Based on their increased sales volume, they could then secure a better purchasing deal.
But instead of pocketing the extra profit, they dropped the price further, to $22.
Costco will even work with vendors to redo its products and processes so as to lower the price, with the savings going to the customer rather than their bottom line.
This strategy toward favoring the customer also coincides with a similar attitude of just how well Costco treats its employees.